Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's daf דף daf is
a continuation of Ayin Bais ע"ב, Ayin Bais, last daf דף daf
for the perek פרק, perek, continuation of yesterday's discussion where Rav Huna
רב הונא Rav Huna said that if somebody
even though when you sell trees the land doesn't go with it,
if you retain ownership of trees, you retain ownership of the land.
And the question is what do we mean by ownership? The Rashbam
רשב"ם Rashbam says literal ownership, the Tosafos תוספות Tosafos says it means
no, no, no, you know if the tree dies then you have
to leave but you have enough ownership while the tree is there
that not only do you have rights to draw on the nutrients
of the land but you even have rights to like plant underneath
it.
And okay, that was his claim. Now the question is, is that
going according to the Rabbanan רבנן Rabbanan where the Rabbis say b'ayin
ra hu mocher בעין רעה הוא מוכר b'ayin ra hu mocher so
it should be pretty obvious same way if you hold possession of
a well you keep possession of the path, if you hold possession
of the tree you have possession of the turf stuff under the
tree. But the claim was it goes even according to Rabbi Akiva
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says b'ayin yafa hu mocher בעין יפה
הוא מוכר b'ayin yafa hu mocher so you think you would give
away the land but here because you need rights of the land
to continue to draw the nutrients then once you already have rights
to the land by necessity according to Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva you're going to have rights to it in a greater way
and going to be able to have rights to actually own it
or to plant under it and so on. That was the statement
of Rav Huna רב הונא. Rav Huna. The attempt then to challenge
Rav Huna רב הונא Rav Huna was, here's my little picture, is
the statement of the Mishnah משנה Mishnah that is if you're makdish
sadeh מקדיש שדה makdish sadeh according to Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon you do not, it's not like a matanah מתנה, matanah, so
the hekdesh הקדש hekdesh does not get the pigeon coop and the
well, but hekdesh הקדש hekdesh does get the tree. What is the
reason that hekdesh הקדש hekdesh gets the tree? So it says well
since the tree is growing from a field of hekdesh הקדש hekdesh
so once you're giving hekdesh הקדש hekdesh the field you're going to
give it the tree as well you don't want the tree to
be growing from a field of hekdesh הקדש, hekdesh, you know your
tree, you'll be getting inappropriate benefit from hekdesh הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, so
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says aha you see that according to Rabbi
Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon this is the you do have in
principle you should be retaining the tree for yourself and nevertheless he
says you do not retain the rights to the ground underneath because
if you retained the rights to the ground underneath then it wouldn't
be a problem that the rest of the field was hekdesh הקדש
hekdesh you would still maintain ownership of the tree. So you see
that according to Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon this is not
true that even when you retain the tree you do not retain
rights to the ground. And the Gemara גמרא Gemara says okay fine,
we'll have to say that Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
work, that Rav Huna's רב הונא Rav Huna statement was only according
to the Rabbanan רבנן Rabbanan of ayin ra hu mocher עין רעה
הוא מוכר ayin ra hu mocher but according to Rabbi Akiva רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva b'ayin yafa hu mocher בעין יפה הוא מוכר b'ayin
yafa hu mocher so yes you're right you do not even when
you retain the tree you do not retain rights to the ground
and since you don't retain rights to the ground and hekdesh הקדש
hekdesh gets all of this then by necessity hekdesh הקדש hekdesh is
going to get the tree as well. All right, so now we
pick up in the Gemara גמרא Gemara on top of Ayin Bais
Amud Aleph ע"ב עמוד א'. Ayin Bais Amud Aleph. U'mi matzis mukmast
lah l'Rabbi Shimon k'Rabbi Akiva ומי מצית מוקמת לה לרבי שמעון כרבי
עקיבא? U'mi matzis mukmast lah l'Rabbi Shimon k'Rabbi Akiva? How can you
say that Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon follows Rabbi Akiva רבי
עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Ve'ha tanya והתניא ve'ha tanya we taught in the
Baraisa ברייתא, Baraisa, well Rabbi Akiva רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was the
Rebbi רבי Rebbi of Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon right so
all of these things Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, Rabbi Meir
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda those were all Talmidei Rabbi Akiva
תלמידי רבי עקיבא. Talmidei Rabbi Akiva. Stam Rabbi Shimon סתם רבי שמעון
Stam Rabbi Shimon by the way is Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
if you're curious. U'mi matzis mukmast lah l'Rabbi Shimon k'Rabbi Akiva ומי
מצית מוקמת לה לרבי שמעון כרבי עקיבא? U'mi matzis mukmast lah l'Rabbi
Shimon k'Rabbi Akiva? How can you say Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is following Rabbi Akiva's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position of ayin
yafa hu mocher עין יפה הוא מוכר? ayin yafa hu mocher? Ve'ha
tanya והתניא ve'ha tanya we taught in the Baraisa ברייתא Baraisa hikdish
shalosh ilanos mimata asara l'beis se'ah הקדיש שלש אילנות ממוטע עשרה לבית
סאה. hikdish shalosh ilanos mimata asara l'beis se'ah. So if you ask
ten trees distributed in the way that each tree will you know
as an equal distribution of ten trees to a beis se'ah בית
סאה, beis se'ah, a beis se'ah בית סאה beis se'ah is fifty
amah אמה amah by fifty amah אמה amah which is twenty-five hundred
square amos אמות amos and you have ten trees like equally distributed
so even if you don't have a beis se'ah בית סאה beis
se'ah you know what it means is that you each tree is
in a space of well divided by ten is in a space
of two hundred and fifty amos אמות amos square amos אמות amos
okay so
all right so you have you sanctified three trees and they were
this degree of distribution so here's your field here's your three trees
and this field is let's say seven hundred and fifty amos אמות
amos okay so the trees are equal are have this type of
a distribution and that's seen as like an appropriate distribution where it's
not too crowded so that you say some trees have to be
uprooted it's not too far away that they're not related to each
other it's the exact right distribution to say that they create like
a field of trees okay so hikdish shalosh ilanos mimata asara l'beis
se'ah הקדיש שלש אילנות ממוטע עשרה לבית סאה hikdish shalosh ilanos mimata
asara l'beis se'ah harei hikdish es hakarka ve'es ha'ilanos she'beinehem הרי הקדיש
את הקרקע ואת האילנות שביניהם harei hikdish es hakarka ve'es ha'ilanos she'beinehem
so in that case you know it not only is the trees
but it includes the land among them because again that's similar to
the principle of one or
two... creates like a field of trees, especially when they're in the
right sort of distribution, therefore implicitly the land goes with that. Okay,
so that's not just our discussion which is like the right to
the row on it and directly under the tree, this is like
the entire, the entire land. הרי זה הקדיש את הקרקע ואת האילנות
שביניהם, harei zeh hikdish et hakarka v'et ha'ilanot shebeineihem, the whole land
and the trees, and trees.
אילנות שביניהם ilanot shebeineihem means if there are other trees that are
here, then those other trees are included. Now of course what you'd
be saying is, one minute Rabbi Linzer, if there are other trees
that are there, then the distribution is not the right distribution because
we said it can't be too crowded, it can't be too dispersed.
So that means that there's small little trees that don't yet bear
fruit, so they're not yet significant enough to change the way we
look at the distribution of the trees. Okay.
These are non-fruit bearing trees?
Well,
I don't know, but anyway if you look at תוספות: tosafot: כגון
אילנות סרק ומשום הכי לא חשבינן להו רצופים דכיון דאין עושין פירות
עומדים לעקר טפי. kegon ilanot srak umishum hachi lo chashvinan lehu retzufin
dikeivan d'ein osin peirot omdim l'aker tefei. Okay, so yes, I mean
the פשט pshat here is that we're talking about non-fruit bearing. What
would be if even the major adult trees were not, I don't
know. Okay, anyway, so in this case you get the land, you
get the small trees, it's all implicitly included. Now why is that
relevant? I mean well, a, it's relevant on its own terms of
course, but here's the other point that this ברייתא baraita is talking
about. That you sanctified this and it's in ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael
and you sanctified this at a time when the יובל yovel was
נוהג. noheig. Now when the יובל yovel is נוהג, noheig, if you
sanctify a שדה אחוזה, sdeh achuza, a field that you have that's
an ancestral field, then the תורה torah tells you the rate in
which you redeem it from הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, fifty שקל כסף shekel
kesef for, you know,
for
חומר בית שעורים. chomer beit se'orim. So for a certain type of
a size you pay fifty כסף kesef for it if you sanctify
it at the beginning of the year, which had to be the
beginning of the יובל, yovel, which is basically, you know, one שקל
כסף shekel kesef per year. So if you're halfway into the יובל,
yovel, it would be, you know, twenty-five or whatever, twenty-four and a
half. Okay, so that's how much, that's if you sanctify a standard
field. The question we're going to be dealing with is, let's say
you sanctified just the trees, how much would you redeem it from
הקדש? hekdesh? Well, whatever the market rate is. Let's say you sanctified
a field that was not a שדה אחוזה, sdeh achuza, that was
some field that you purchased, that was not an ancestral field. How
much would you redeem it for? The market rate. The תורה's torah
setting of the fixed price only applies to a שדה אחוזה. sdeh
achuza. So here the question is going to be, do you, this
is two units? I sanctify trees and I sanctify the field, so
the fields I redeem at the תורה's torah rate, the trees I
redeem at market price. Or do you say, no, what do you
mean? Since the field came together with the trees and the field
was only sanctified by virtue of the trees, obviously you look at
it as one unit, so you sanctify the whole thing, field and
trees at the תורה's torah fixed price. So that's the issue of
the ברייתא. baraita. Let's take a look.
Maybe that's why we talk about fruit-bearing trees because of the שעורים?
se'orim?
Could be. כשהוא פודה, keshehu podeh, when he redeems this field that
you just sanctified, פודה בית זרע חומר שעורים, podeh beit zera chomer
se'orim, so a field of חומר שעורים, chomer se'orim, a planting, the
certain unit of barley. I think that's this בית סאה, beit se'ah,
I think that that's the same here.
You sanctify it בחמישים שקל כסף. bachamishim shekel kesef. That's the fixed
price of the תורה torah for a שדה אחוזה. sdeh achuza. פחות
מכאן או יותר על כן, pachot mikan o yoter al ken, if
the trees are more condensed or more spread out, so you don't,
the field doesn't go with the trees. In that case, only the
trees are sanctified. או שהקדישן בזה אחר זה, o shehikdishan bzeh achar
zeh, or let's say
you
actually sanctified the trees and the field but you did it in
two stages. Okay, so maybe you sanctified the trees individually: first this
tree and this tree and this. It's only when you sanctify all
three does the field come with it. So you sanctified the trees
individually, or the trees were too spread out or too or too
condensed so the field doesn't go with it. In either of those
scenarios the field doesn't go with it. הרי
זה לא הקדיש לא את הקרקע ולא את האילנות שביניהם. harei zeh
lo hikdish lo et hakarka v'lo et ha'ilanot shebeineihem. So in that
case when the trees are too condensed or too spread out or
you do the trees individually, you don't get the land and you
don't get the small trees in between them. That's number one. הקדש
hekdesh only gets the trees themselves. Okay. לפיכך כשהוא פודה פודה את
האילנות כשוויהן, lefi-chach keshehu podeh podeh et ha'ilanot keshiveihen,
and therefore if you're going to redeem it, you'll redeem the trees
at market price. You only sanctified trees, you didn't sanctify a field.
The תורה's torah הלכה halakha about the fixed price, the fixed rate
is when you sanctify the field. ולא עוד, v'lo od, not only
that, אלא אפילו הקדיש את האילנות וחזר והקדיש את הקרקע, ela afilu
hikdish et ha'ilanot v'chazar v'hikdish et hakarka, let's say you sanctified the
trees separately because they were either too condensed or too spread out
or you did them individually, not as a unit of three. So
now the trees are sanctified but the field is not, and now
you sanctify the field. Okay. כשהוא פודה, keshehu podeh, doesn't matter, you
have two separate units here. So therefore כשהוא פודה פודה את האילנות
כשוויהן, keshehu podeh podeh et ha'ilanot keshiveihen, you redeem the trees at
market price. the trees at their market rate, וחזר פודה בדרך חומש
וחמישים שקל כסף vechozar podeh bederech chomesh vechamishim shekel kesef and then
you go ahead and you redeem the field based on the fixed
rate in the Torah. Okay, so that's a you know, the principle
here is pretty clear. When it's the whole, when it's the entire
field and the field comes as a unit with the stuff in
it, you then look at the whole thing as a unit. And
if it's a שדה אחוזה, Sedeh Achozah, it's based on the fixed
rate in the Torah. When they are separate units, okay, even if
it's the same physical setup, right, that's the חידוש, chiddush, it could
be the exact same physical setup, right? That these are correctly distributed
within that field, but because הקדש Hekdesh first got the trees and
then the field because you sanctified the trees individually so they didn't
catch the field together with it. In that case, conceptually you have
two separate things here that were sanctified to הקדש, Hekdesh, and the
field is sanctified based on the fixed rate and the trees based
on the market rate.
Okay, we did earlier and
let's say you're מקדיש makdish the field then I assume that, yeah,
then the trees go with it and then yeah it would, if
you start with the field, it would all be go based on
the fixed rate. Right, I guess it would be an interesting question
whether that would go to our משנה Mishnah and the debate in
our משנה. Mishnah. Let's say these trees were like the carob and
the sycamore, so, you know, but let's, putting aside רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon for a moment, assuming the trees would always go with the
field then it would all be one unit.
Rabbi, could you just say, just clarify something a little more basic,
like I'm מקדיש makdish my field. Right. So then if I'm פודה
podeh the field what have I done?
You've brought it back from הקדש. Hekdesh. You've given הקדש Hekdesh money
and you've gotten your field back.
Oh, right, so the first thing you could do that is as
a matter of standard practice? I could מקדיש makdish even an animal
and then I've...
Well, if you're מקדיש makdish an animal and it's not a בעל
מום baal mum and it's a תמים, tamim, it's without blemish, then
it sort of gets becomes a קרבן korban and then it becomes
more complicated.
Right, it's for the economy of the מקדש.
Mikdash. Yeah, the בדק הבית.
Bedek Habayis. Right, I can be מקדיש makdish the field, I'll use
it for a while then I'll buy it back and I'll give
them the money.
Right, or they could never, or they could not have used it
at all, right, exactly.
Are they used to take the money and they can keep the
field?
No, no, you have a right to be פודה. podeh.
Yeah, you have a right to exercise.
Yeah, exactly. Of course you have to also add a חומש, chomesh,
but anyway that's different for a moment.
Right. Anyway, yeah, fine, let's go. So now it says like this,
okay, now why is all of this relevant? Money. Who is this
ברייתא? braisa? This ברייתא. braisa. אי רבי עקיבא, Ei Rabbi Akiva, המוכר
בעין יפה מוכר, hamocher be'ayin yafah mocher, וכל שכן מקדיש. vechol shekein
makdish. So the question is now, if it's רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
meaning it's a funny assumption question the גמרא Gemara makes here. The
גמרא Gemara sort of assumes that
when
you sanctify the trees individually, it sounds like you only sanctify the
trees, right? Not there's no discussion in this ברייתא braisa of the
possibility that when you did the trees individually some of the land
came with the trees. Now, of course, that wasn't the interest of
the ברייתא. braisa. The ברייתא braisa wasn't talking about the land directly
under, it was talking about the whole space. But the גמרא Gemara
assumes, at least this is the way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it,
okay, that it sounds like when you do the trees individually, not
as three, so the land doesn't come with it, no land comes
with the trees. Okay, so that's our question. Who is that going
like? So when you sanctify the tree it's only the tree and
not the land underneath it? So מאני, mani, who is that going
like? אי רבי עקיבא, Ei Rabbi Akiva, if it's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, המוכר בעין יפה מוכר, hamocher be'ayin yafah mocher, that you sell
with a generous eye, so the same way in even a sale,
this is הקדש, Hekdesh, הקדש Hekdesh we should assume is more generous.
So the same way if I sell you my well, I give
you a path to my well, when I מקדיש makdish the tree,
some of the land under the tree should go with it. And
this makes it sound again, it really doesn't say it directly, but
that if you're מקדיש makdish just one tree, no land goes with
it. וכל שכן מקדיש. vechol shekein makdish. Okay, so it can't be
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אי רבנן, Ei rabanan, now if it's the
Rabbis, הא אמרי מוכר הוא דבעין רעה מוכר. ha amri mocher hu
debe'ayin ra'ah mocher.
Remember in the משנה Mishnah the Rabbis, when did they say that,
you know, you only gave partly, that was when you sold it.
אבל הקדש aval Hekdesh that it's a מוכר mocher who does it
with a stingy eye, בעין רעה מוכר. be'ayin ra'ah mocher. אבל מקדיש,
aval makdish, but remember the Rabbis of the משנה Mishnah said מקדיש
makdish is like נותן מתנה nosein matanah and everything goes with it.
אבל מקדיש בעין יפה מקדיש. aval makdish be'ayin yafah makdish. So the
גמרא Gemara is saying who is it that says when you do
the trees individually you get no land underneath? It's מקדיש. makdish. So
presumably everybody should agree you get at least some of the land
under. אלא פשיטא, ela peshita, so who is the only one in
our משנה Mishnah that treats מקדיש makdish as a stingy type of
a transaction? That's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. That רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says when you're מקדיש makdish the field you don't get this stuff
in it, okay? So you only get the field and הקדש Hekdesh
doesn't get the other stuff. So this would have to be רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who would say you give הקדש Hekdesh the tree
and nothing under the tree, that even מקדיש makdish is with a
stinginess. אלא פשיטא רבי שמעון היא. ela peshita Rabbi Shimon hi. Okay,
that's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, fine. Now, רבי שמעון אליבא דמאן. Rabbi
Shimon aliba deman. Now, which רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, there's two
issues here. One is, is הקדש Hekdesh like מתנה matanah or is
הקדש Hekdesh like מכר? mecher? Is הקדש Hekdesh with generosity or is
it with הקדש Hekdesh with the normal type of limited scope as
a מכר? mecher? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, remember... that you
do not get the stuff in the field with הקדש, hekdesh, that
הקדש hekdesh is not with generosity, it's not like מתנה, matana, it's
like מכר. mecher. But now, now that we've, that's one question. The
other question is even within the context of מכר, mecher, is it
בעין יפה be'ayin yaffa or בעין רעה? be'ayin ra'a? Right? So there's
the, right, everybody get that? Meaning, meaning, just to remind you, רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva who says מוכר בעין יפה מוכר, mocher be'ayin yaffa
mocher, that's limited. That means if I sell Michael my well, he
gets to pass to the well. But if המקדיש hamakdish or מתנה,
matana, then it's much more generous. It includes like everything in the
field. Okay? So the first question is, is מקדיש makdish like a
gift or like מכר? mecher? So it's only רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
who says that מקדיש makdish is like מכר, mecher, it's limited. But
then within that we have to say, okay, but within the more
limited scope of מוכר, mocher, is it with generosity or with stinginess,
בעין יפה, be'ayin yaffa, בעין רעה? be'ayin ra'a? So let's take a
look. Okay? Now, ואליבא דמאן? ve'aliba deman? רבי שמעון אליבא דמאן? Rebbi
Shimon aliba deman? אי אליבא דרבי עקיבא, ei aliba deRebbi Akiva, if
it's according to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, who says that, okay, even
within מוכר mocher there's still a generosity, הא אמר מוכר בעין יפה
מוכר וכל שכן מקדיש. ha amar mocher be'ayin yaffa mocher vechol shekein
makdish. But says wait, but if even if all it had was
the generosity of מוכר, mocher, the same way when I sell somebody
a well, they get access to the well, when I would sell
somebody a tree, they should get the rights of the land underneath
the tree. That's an assumption for רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. So this
idea that you sold, you were מקדיש makdish this tree, a) we
can't be talking about the standard רבנן, Rabbanan, the standard approach that
הקדש hekdesh is like מתנה, matana, because then you obviously would get
a lot and you would get some of the field. Even if
הקדש hekdesh is like מכר, mecher, it can't be a רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva מכר mecher because then together with the tree you'd get
some of the land, and this is assuming with the tree comes
none of the land. So the only way this makes sense is
if it is the stingiest read possible. Okay? That מקדיש makdish is
like מכר mecher and like the stingy מוכר, mocher, like the רבנן's
Rabbanan מוכר. mocher. So even though I'm giving הקדש hekdesh the tree,
they get nothing of the land. Okay? So אלא פשיטא אליבא דרבנן.
ela peshita aliba deRabbanan. It must be that this is going like
the רבנן. Rabbanan. דקסבר רבי שמעון, dekasavar Rebbi Shimon, now, but now
all of this was to lead up to our challenging of רב
הונא. Rav Huna. Because וקסבר רבי שמעון כי היכי דבמוכר בעין רעה
מוכר מקדיש נמי בעין רעה מקדיש, vekasavar Rebbi Shimon ki heichi debemocher
be'ayin ra'a mocher makdish nami be'ayin ra'a makdish, the same way when
you sell it, it's with a stinginess, when you're מקדיש makdish it's
with a stinginess, ומשייר ארעא, umeshayar ar'a, and you're leaving the land
and you are only giving the tree and not the land underneath
it. So now we've got a question. Here we see according to
the רבנן, Rabbanan, when I give a tree, I give it with
הקדש, hekdesh, I give it with none of the land underneath it,
according to רבי שמעון's Rebbi Shimon version of the רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay?
But so, so how does that fit with what רב הונא Rav
Huna taught? Because רב הונא Rav Huna taught that if you, that
you know, and now of course there's a difference here, but the
question is רב הונא Rav Huna taught that when you retain a
tree, right, you sort of retain the land that is underneath it.
Now of course there's a difference because here you're not retaining the
tree, you're giving the tree. So the בעין רעה be'ayin ra'a could
say, I give you the tree like without the land underneath it.
So it's a little bit unclear exactly what the גמרא's Gemara question
is. What the גמרא Gemara shown here is that according to the
רבנן, Rabbanan, when I give the tree, I don't give any of
the land, assuming that מקדיש makdish is like מוכר. mocher. So if
I were to be מקדיש makdish according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
or מוכר mocher according to the רבנן Rabbanan the tree, none of
the land would go with it. Okay, but why is that a
problem? The claim of רב הונא Rav Huna was when I keep
the tree, I keep the land underneath it. So it's not exactly
clear what the challenge is. The רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot try
to really like figure out the exact question here. Let's
see the גמרא's Gemara answer because it's hard to understand exactly fully
what the question is. Yes.
He means if he would take the tree out, he doesn't leave
the tree.
Yeah, that's exactly the point. So you see though the tree comes
by itself and it comes without, without the land. Okay?
So, yes, something similar?
Well, that, well, you wouldn't take it, you could in theory but
I mean also הקדש hekdesh would, if you wanted to redeem the
tree, you would just pay the value of the tree and not
any of the value of the land underneath it. Right? But I
mean, yeah, I guess if you refused to redeem it, הקדש hekdesh
would come and pull out the tree or הקדש hekdesh might sell
it to some other party or something. Yeah. Okay. So anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So recognizing that we don't really fully understand the question, let's find
out the answer. ולא קשיא הא דינקא מארעא דהקדש. velo kashya ha
dyanka me'ar'a dehekdesh.
So okay, so then if this is true, that this רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon here, now we've shown that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon follows
the רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay? So let's say רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon here
follows the רבנן. Rabbanan. Fine. Now let's get back to here. This
the רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon of the משנה. Mishna. So the רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon of the משנה Mishna says is that this is
really the point. Here you see that the only way to make
sense is to assume that there's a רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon out
there who holds like the רבנן. Rabbanan. That מקדיש makdish is like
מוכר mochar and מוכר mochar is בעין רעה. be'ayin ra. So with
that in mind, going back to this, you sanctify this field to
הקדש. Hekdesh. So if you sanctify this field to הקדש Hekdesh and
you're this is what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says and you're doing
it in the stingy way אליבא דרבנן. aliba de'Rabbanan. So if when
you sell the tree you're not, you know, so if the רבנן
Rabbanan are the stingy sort of version of the רבנן, Rabbanan, you're
selling it and you're retaining the land. So when you're keeping the
tree, you're certainly retaining the land. Okay? So then why again does
the tree become קדוש? kadosh? This is רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon according
to the we said before it was רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon according
to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, and when you sanctify the land then
it's all of the land and then the tree by necessity becomes
קדוש. kadosh. But here we've proven that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon holds
like the רבנן. Rabbanan. That the only way to make sense of
this of this ברייתא braita was saying it was going according to
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, מקדיש makdish is like מוכר, mochar, it's בעין
רעה, be'ayin ra, הקדש Hekdesh gets the tree, doesn't get the land.
Fine. So if רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon goes like the רבנן, Rabbanan,
when you keep the tree you certainly keep the land. And since
you and since you certainly keep the land, why does the tree
become קדוש? kadosh? Let's I don't want to hear any maybes, I
we gotta hold cup here. Okay? So everybody see from this ברייתא
braita we've established that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon must hold like A.
מקדיש makdish is like מוכר mochar and B. מוכר mochar is בעין
רעה be'ayin ra like the רבנן, Rabbanan, and therefore when you give
הקדש Hekdesh the tree you only give הקדש Hekdesh the tree. So
if רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is like the רבנן, Rabbanan, when you
retain the tree here and you're מקדיש makdish the field, you should
retain the ground underneath it and the tree shouldn't become קדוש. kadosh.
So we're back to our question of how do you read like
this case, why according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon does the tree
become קדוש? kadosh?
Is it the same kind of tree in both cases?
Yes, let's assume. ואלא קשיא, V'ela kashya, so now we have a
problem, הרי יונקים משדה הקדש? hov yonkim mis'deh hekdesh? How do you
explain that idea that they draw the nutrients out of the הקדש
Hekdesh field? Why does it draw the nutrients? Why doesn't that field
under the tree still belong to you?
אלא Ela fine, רבי שמעון לדבריהם דרבנן קאמר להו. Rebbi Shimon l'divreihem
de'Rabbanan ka-amar lehu. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is saying according to the
Rabbis: לדידי, L'didi, as far as I'm concerned, כי היכי דמוכר בעין
רעה מוכר, k'eiha d'mochar be'ayin ra mochar, מקדיש נמי בעין רעה מקדיש.
makdish nami be'ayin ra makdish. I say the same way when you
sell it you're stingy, when you're מקדיש makdish you're stingy. ושיורי משייר,
ushiyuri meshayer, and you leave over. So as far as I'm concerned,
says רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon in this case, because here we see
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon holds like the רבנן, Rabbanan, that even a
מקדיש makdish is stingy. So therefore I say דמקדיש d'makdish you're stingy,
you keep the coop, you keep the well, you keep the land
under the tree, and you would keep the tree to yourself. As
far as I'm concerned, you would keep the tree to yourself. That's
not again פשט p'shat of the משנה, Mishna, but that's what we're
saying. That's as far as I'm concerned. I say you're stingy. אלא,
Ela, he says, לדידכו, l'didchu, מוכר מקדיש בעין רעה מוכר ושיורי משייר,
mochar makdish be'ayin ra mochar ushiyuri meshayer, ולדידכו v'l'didchu according to you
that you say, אודו לי מיהת odu li mi'at דלא הקדיש אלא
חרובא המורכב וסדן השקמה. d'lo hikdish ela charuva hamurkav v'sadan hashikma. But
according to you that you're generous, I guess he says that the
generosity extends to the entire field. And since your generosity of הקדש
Hekdesh extends to the entire field, it also extends to the tree
which grows from the field. But what I don't get is why
even with you and all of your generosity you're selling the pigeon
coop and the and the well which are separate from the field.
You want to give the field and the whole field under the
tree and therefore it gets the tree, געזונטהייט. gezuntaheit. But that's all
an extension of being מקדיש makdish the field. But why are you
saying that הקדש Hekdesh gets these things as well? Okay, that's getting
a little bit overly generous. That's not the field, that's something separate
from the field. Okay? ואמרו ליה רבנן לא שנא. V'amru lei Rabbanan
lo shna. And they say nah,
doesn't matter, we think you're very generous when you give to הקדש,
Hekdesh, the same way by the way when you give a מתנה
matana you're generous. Okay, so basically what we've said is is that
when he says that you get this but not this, he's really
saying that would what I would say that even the rabbis who
say generous it should be this but not me who says stingy
and we've learned down here that he follows the stingy approach of
בעין רעה. be'ayin ra. Me who says stingy, I would say that
you
retain owner right to the field underneath, and since you retain right
to the field underneath the tree, the tree itself is not הקדש.
Hekdesh. And that ultimately gets us back to רב הונא Rabb Huna's
idea that when you retain the tree, you retain rights to the
field underneath the tree. Okay, let's go on.
So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, now we're still not done. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says במאי אוקימתא לה כרבי שמעון? Bemai ukimta lah k'Rabbi Shimon?
So who did you say that the that this ברייתא, braita, now
we're back here to this ברייתא braita being מקדיש makdish it in
two stages or whatever, who did you say this ברייתא braita was
going according to? Like Rabbi Shimon, and that's why when you do
individual trees, you don't get the field underneath, you only get the
trees. במאי אוקימתא לה b'mai okimta la כרבי שמעון? k'Rebbi Shimon? Like
Rabbi Shimon? אימא סיפא. Eima seifa. Let's look at the end of
that ברייתא. Baraita. ולא עוד אלא אפילו הקדיש את האילנות וחזר והקדיש
את הקרקע. V'lo od ela afilu hikdish et ha'ilanot v'chazar v'hikdish et
hakarka. If you were to sanctify the trees individually, so that it
wasn't three trees at once and you didn't get the field at
once, so you did each tree individually and then after the trees
were קדוש, kadosh, you sanctified the land. כשהוא פודה פודה את האילנות
בשוייהן. Keshehu podeh, podeh et ha'ilanot b'shaveihen.
Now when you redeem it, you redeem the trees in terms of
their market value. וחזר פודה בית זרע חומר שעורים בחמישים שקל כסף.
V'chazar podeh beit zera chomer se'orim b'chamishim shekel kesef. And then you
redeem the field based on
the
standard rate, or the Torah's fixed rate of redeeming a שדה אחוזה.
sdei achuza. So the גמרא Gemara says: Now, so you're saying this
ברייתא Baraita is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, and that's why the
trees came only by themselves without the קרקע. karka. But now I've
got another problem. That idea of what rate you redeem the field
on by הקדש hekdesh doesn't fit with another position of רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, a new idea of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. והא רבי
שמעון בתר פדיון אזיל וניקוף אגב ארעייהו. V'ha Rabbi Shimon batar pidyon
azil v'neikof agav araiyahu.
According to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we're going to see from some
other place that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that even if when
you're מקדיש makdish something, it was in a certain state at the
time of being מקדיש makdish it, when you come to redeem it,
you look at the state it is now that it's being redeemed.
So even if this were sanctified in two stages, first the tree
and now the field, right now you have a קדוש kadosh field
with trees. So we should look at that as one unit, and
you should be able to redeem it as one unit and not
as two separate units. So okay, right? Because that's the thing. If
I was מקדיש makdish the field with the trees as one unit,
I would be redeeming it as one unit and it would be
based on the fixed rate. The only reason now you're saying that
they first redeem the trees based on their market value and then
the field is that they were sanctified in two separate states.
But we're going to the amount of money, it's the same amount?
No, it is not. Like I've been saying, the field has the
fixed rate in the Torah. With or without trees, whether it's rich
land or not rich land. Okay? So if they're doing it as
one unit, you're not paying any extra for the trees. But if
you're doing it as a separate unit, you redeem the trees at
the market rate and the field at the fixed rate. So now,
the only reason רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that there are two
redemptions that occur here is because it was sanctified in two stages.
But I'm going to show you, says the גמרא, Gemara, that there's
a different רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in another place that says that
we don't look at the stages in which something was sanctified, we
look at the end result. And at the end result, you have
a field with trees, it should be one redemption based on the
fixed rate and not two redemptions. So let's take a look. So
it says like this: והא דשמענא ליה לרבי שמעון אזיל בתר פדיון.
V'ha d'shamana lei l'Rabbi Shimon azil batar pidyon. We know רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon goes by the time of redemption, not the stages of
הקדש. hekdesh. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: מניין ללוקח
שדה מאביו והקדישה ואחר כך מת אביו מניין שתהא לפניו כשדה אחוזה?
Minayin l'lokeach sadeh me'aviv v'hikdishah v'achar kach met aviv minayin shetehei lefanav
k'sdei achuza?
So here is what happens: You've got here
יעקב. Yaakov. Okay, and now you've got ראובן. Reuven. Okay, and now
you've got יעקב's Yaakov field. Okay, now ראובן Reuven goes ahead, now
that's owned by יעקב. Yaakov. While יעקב Yaakov is alive, what's the
case? מניין ללוקח שדה מאביו והקדישה ואחר כך מת אביו. Minayin l'lokeach
sadeh me'aviv v'hikdishah v'achar kach met aviv.
So first he buys it. Okay, number one is he buys it
from his father.
Then he's מקדיש makdish it.
Okay, that's stage number two. And then stage number three, יעקב Yaakov
dies. Okay, so
when he was מקדיש makdish it, it was not yet a שדה
אחוזה, sdei achuza, right? When he was מקדיש makdish it, it was
a purchased field. If יעקב Yaakov had died first, he would have
inherited the field, it would have been a שדה אחוזה. sdei achuza.
But at this stage, it's only a purchased field. If you're מקדיש
makdish a purchased field, you redeem it based on market rate. You
don't redeem it based on the fixed rate in the Torah.
And his father would have gotten the field back had his father
lived.
Right, that's important to note as well, that had his father been
alive and he would have bought it, let's say he wouldn't have
been מקדיש. makdish. When he's buying it from his father and his
father's alive, when the יובל Yovel hits, but while his father's still
alive, it goes back to the father. So it's not even just
a fiction to call it a purchased field. It's not like oh,
it's purchased but
somehow it's going to be his anyway. It will go back depending
on when יובל Yovel hits and when his father's alive, it will
go back to the father. Okay, so when he was מקדיש makdish
it here, he was מקדיש makdish a field that he did not,
that was a purchased field that as Charlie correctly said, he doesn't
even fully own. It's a field that will go back to his
father in the יובל. Yovel. And
then his father dies. And now he wants to redeem it. So
you would logically think he has to redeem this like a purchased
field, right? Not based on the fixed rate of the Torah, because
when he was מקדיש makdish it, that's the state it was in.
But we're going to see רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going to
say no, now that he's coming to be פודה, podeh, which is
a stage of... stage number four, okay,
right? Now that יאנקל Yankel was at stage number four as he's
coming to be פודה, podeh, now he's coming to be פודה, podeh,
יאנקל Yankel is already dead. So since יאנקל Yankel is already dead,
we sort of say, well, had
now that יאנקל Yankel is dead, the field had he still owned
the field, would have been a שדה אחוזה, sedeh achozah, right, had
he not been מקדיש makdish it yet. It would have been a
שדה אחוזה, sedeh achozah, he would have at this stage inherited it
from יאנקל. Yankel. Let's assume there are no other brothers, which will
complicate things. Okay. So since at the time of being פודה podeh
it, his relationship to the field is something he would have inherited
from his father, he redeems it as the שדה אחוזה sedeh achozah
at the fixed rate of the תורה Torah and not as a
שדה מקנה, sedeh miknah, which is the state it was in when
he was מקדיש makdish it. Now that sounds completely bizarre, right? But
nevertheless, that shows you how far רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon goes, that
says you redeem something, you do it based on the state it's
in when you redeem it, not when you're מקדיש makdish it. So
if that's true, why in our case of the tree, of the
trees, you should just do redeem the whole field as one unit
even though you were מקדיש makdish it as two units? Because when
you redeem it, it's one unit. The same way here when you
redeem it, you look at it as a שדה אחוזה, sedeh achozah,
not as a שדה מקנה. sedeh miknah. Let me just read the
line inside and then you're going to ask your questions. Okay. מנין
ללוקח
שדה מאביו והקדישה ואחר כך מת אביו מנין
שתהא לפניו כשדה אחוזה? Minayin lalokeach sedeh me-aviv vehikdishah ve-achar kach met
aviv minayin she-tehei lefanav ke-sedeh achozah? How do you know you treat
it like a שדה אחוזה? sedeh achozah? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ואם
את שדה מקנתו Ve-im et sedeh miknato אשר לא משדה אחוזתו, asher
lo mi-sedeh achozato, that is not an inherited field. Why do you
have to say that? Just say a purchased field. So, שדה שאינה
ראויה להיות שדה אחוזה. Sedeh she-einah re-uyah lihyot sedeh achozah. We're talking
about a field that was only purchased that was no way considered
like fit to be a שדה אחוזה. sedeh achozah. יצא זו שראויה
להיות שדה אחוזה, Yatza zu she-re-uyah lihyot sedeh achozah, דברי רבי יהודה
ורבי שמעון. divrei Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Shimon. Which means this, which was
a purchased field, but a purchased field that could be a שדה
אחוזה, sedeh achozah, that's treated as a שדה אחוזה. sedeh achozah. Now
the could be here means a specific could be. I mean, even
if יאנקל Yankel had not died, it could have been a שדה
אחוזה sedeh achozah had יאנקל Yankel died. But the could be here
is interpreted in a limited way. Could be means that had he
not purchased it, by now it already would have been a שדה
אחוזה. sedeh achozah. So since this field, had he not purchased it
from יאנקל, Yankel, at this stage when he's coming to be פודה,
podeh, it would have been a שדה אחוזה sedeh achozah had he
not purchased it, we're going to still treat it as a שדה
אחוזה sedeh achozah and he's going to redeem it as a שדה
אחוזה. sedeh achozah. That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon say. So you say we look at things at the
stage they are in when the time it comes to be פודה.
podeh. What could this have looked like? Okay, and we're more ready
to categorize things as a שדה אחוזה sedeh achozah to go by
the fixed rate of the תורה. Torah. So the same way we're
going to categorize this as a שדה אחוזה, sedeh achozah, we should
look at this as one unit as a שדה אחוזה sedeh achozah
and do it as, you know, one redemption, not as two separate
ones. That's the argument. So how can רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon here
says that it's two redemptions? You had a question?
I just think there's a logical problem with the argument. In other
words, it doesn't prove that it doesn't prove that you assess the
value of the land at the time of the פדיון pidyon as
opposed to the time of the הקדשה. hakdashah. Right.
It's an analogy, that's true. This could be a special rule about
is it in the category of שדה אחוזה sedeh achozah or שדה
מקנה? sedeh miknah? And this is, do you look at the things
in it as separate units or not? I understand they're not the
same. But the point is, since here we're more inclined to categorize
something as a שדה אחוזה sedeh achozah and look and focus at
at the time of פדיון pidyon what it would have been, so
okay, the גמרא Gemara says yes, you could have made a distinction,
but the גמרא's Gemara saying then logically we should look at this
as one unit and not as two units even though it was
sanctified as two units. Yes.
I'm confused as to why a person should ever be able to
make a purchase field הקדש. hekdesh.
Oh, because you know he doesn't own it enough. So essentially what
he's only doing is he's being מקדיש makdish the, you know, the
sort of the lease that he has effectively. It's a קנין פירות
kinyan peirot question as well. If I buy a field from you
during the time of יובל Yovel and there's 20 years to יובל,
Yovel, what I really have is a קנין גוף לפירות לעשרים שנה.
kinyan guf le-peirot le-esrim shanah. So when I מקדיש, makdish, I מקדיש
makdish my ownership of that field. But you only have it
for 10 years and יובל Yovel 20 years from now. Then what?
Right, so then you get it back. ויצא, veyatza, what is it?
I think it goes back to the בעלים be'alim ביובל. be-Yovel. I
give what?
And you're not done, you don't have to worry about מעילה? me'ilah?
You're not misusing?
Right, because what I've done was, and now I've got to look
at the
פסוקים, pesukim, just give me a חומש. Chumash. Right.
So let's say it's a 10
year lease, yeah,
let's say it's 10 yearly and יובל Yovel 20 years from now,
then what? What
are you מקדיש? makdish? What? I bought it for 10 years, right?
And יובל Yovel 20 years from now.
So then you're מקדיש makdish those 10 years.
And then it just stops?
Yeah, because then it comes, hold on.
Yeah. Thank you.
Not כח, kaf-chet, not כח, kaf-chet, hold on. Oh, yes, it is.
Wait. כז כח. kaf-zayin kaf-chet. כב, kaf-bet, כב. kaf-bet. ואם משדה מקנתו
אשר לא משדה אחזתו יקדיש להשם וחשב לו הכהן את מכסת הערכך
עד שנת היובל ונתן את הערכך ביום ההוא קדש להשם.
V'im misedei miknaso asher lo misedei achuzaso yakdish l'Hashem vechishav lo hakohein
es machsas erkecha ad shnas hayovel v'nosan es ha'erkecha bayom hahu kodesh
l'Hashem. בשנת היובל ישוב השדה לאשר קנהו מאיתו לאשר לו אחזת הארץ.
Bishnas hayovel yashuv hasadeh la'asher kanahu me'ito la'asher lo achuzas ha'aretz. Yeah.
So it just magically now becomes הקדש. hekdesh.
Right, because הקדש hekdesh got for a twenty-year lease of that land,
they got that ownership. So then that ownership, I gave them what
I had, and then when that ran out, it went back to
the owner. Yeah.
That's a very weird sort of mechanism for הקדש hekdesh to come
in.
Well, right,
but they never owned the title to the land itself; they owned
the rights of usage for those twenty years. They owned the קנין
פירות kinyan peiros for those twenty years. Okay. It should be more
value.
What? Which should be a higher price?
Oh, I think that the market, well, you never know, depends how
good the land is, how good the trees are. But anyway, but
separating it into two is definitely a higher price, because you're paying
a fixed value for the land, and the question is, are you
also paying the market value for the trees? But whether the fixed
value or the market value depends on how good the land is
and depends what the market looks like. Okay, so let's keep on
going. So it says like this. Okay, that's רבי יהודה ברבי שמעון.
Rabbi Yehuda bar Rabbi Shimon. רבי מאיר אומר מניין ללוקח שדה מאביו
ומת אביו ואחר כך הקדיש? Rabbi Meir omer minayin l'lokeach sadeh me'aviv
umes aviv v'achar kach hikdish? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, no
no, I'll tell you—not רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who's this? רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. I'll tell you when I agree with you. I agree
with you if the order is different. I'll agree with you if
he purchases it and then יעקב Yaakov dies and then you're מקדיש.
makdish. Because then, before you even did the act of הקדש, hekdesh,
it already was an inherited field. Now, you could say one minute,
it's only a theoretical inherited field; in practice, he actually purchased it.
It's true that then his father died, but his father died after
he already owned the field. But here's the point, and this was
I forget who made this point earlier, Eli or whatever, the point
is that something did happen when יעקב Yaakov died. When he purchased
it, okay, he only had rights to that field until the יובל.
yovel. Now that יעקב Yaakov died, he has permanent ownership of that
field. Okay, so it starts as a שדה מקנה, sadeh miknah, then
יעקב Yaakov dies, then it really does become a שדה אחוזה. sadeh
achuzah. His ownership now has increased; he fully has title to it.
Then he's מקדיש makdish it. He says, that I'll already call a
שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuzah. That's not such a huge חידוש. chiddush. Okay,
I mean, it's a little חידוש, chiddush, because you could have said
since he started with it as a שדה מקנה, sadeh miknah, it
retains that status. And the answer is no. Since יעקב Yaakov died
and he fully owns it now, it's a שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuzah.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, that I'll concede to you, that
then it's a שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuzah. But the reverse order, no
way. You were sanctified it when it was a שדה מקנה, sadeh
miknah, it's considered a שדה מקנה. sadeh miknah. Okay, so רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says: מניין ללוקח שדה מאביו ומת אביו ואחר כך הקדיש?
minayin l'lokeach sadeh me'aviv umes aviv v'achar kach hikdish? So the father
died and then you sanctified. מניין שתהא לפניו כשדה אחוזה? minayin she'tehei
lifanav k'sadeh achuzah? That, how do I know it's a שדה אחוזה
sadeh achuzah and it goes by the fixed
rate? תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar: ואם משדה מקנתו אשר לא משדה אחוזתו.
v'im misedei miknaso asher lo misedei achuzaso. That if it's a שדה
מקנה sadeh miknah that's not a שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuzah. שדה שאינה
שדה אחוזה, sadeh she'einah sadeh achuzah, not that it does not fit
in theory to be a שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuzah. In practice it's
not a שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuzah. יצאת זו שהיא שדה אחוזה. yatzas
zu shehi sadeh achuzah. This which really is a שדה אחוזה, sadeh
achuzah, became a שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuzah, that's one thing. But if
you were sanctifying it when it was a שדה מקנה, sadeh miknah,
even though now when you're פודה podeh it, it theoretically could have
been a שדה אחוזה sadeh achuzah had you sort
of, you know, done a different order. Okay, so רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is bothered by that.
Right, I mean, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's position is a strange one.
Okay.
ואילו רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון, v'ilu Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Shimon, היכא דמת
אביו ואחר כך הקדישה, heicha d'mes aviv v'achar kach hikdishah, when the
father died and then you were sanctified it, לא צריכי קרא. lo
tzrichi kra. For them that's obvious. כי אצטריך קרא, ki itzterich kra,
no, they're making a bigger חידוש. chiddush. היכא דהקדישה ואחר כך מת
אביו, heicha d'hikdishah v'achar kach mes aviv, right? That you were מקדיש
makdish it as a שדה מקנה, sadeh miknah, then the father died,
so then when you get to being פודה podeh it you say,
well, theoretically it could have been a שדה אחוזה sadeh achuzah had
you sort of, you know, done a different order. Okay, so that's
what they say. ואחר—so
כי אצטריך קרא היכא דהקדישה ואחר כך מת אביו. ki itzterich kra
heicha d'hikdishah v'achar kach mes aviv. מנלן? menalan? Where do they get
an idea that in this case it should be treated as a
שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuzah, since when you were מקדיש makdish it, it
was still a שדה מקנה? sadeh miknah? So מנלן? menalan? אי מהקרא.
i mehakra. It can't just be a פסוק, pasuk, because if you
just had a פסוק, pasuk, אימא כרבי מאיר דאתא. eima k'Rabbi Meir
de'asa. You know, they could have used the פסוק pasuk like רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, which by the way is very important because what
it shows you is, for people that grow up in learning in
ישיבה, yeshiva, you know, you're sort of, the message is like, you
know, all of the different opinions are just straight questions of you
look at the פסוקים psukim and how do you interpret this word,
how do you interpret that word. Of course, the point is like,
okay, but what makes one Rabbi read this extra word or this
extra letter this way and the other that way? So you know,
so is it a pure like technical consideration? So sometimes it's like
maybe it has to do with the assumptions you bring to the
text, right, and what's your general sort of way of thinking about
the idea and then what do you read when you have a
something in a פסוק pasuk that tells you something. So here they're
debating how do you read the phrase אם משדה מקנתו אשר לא.
im misedei miknaso asher lo. משתחזותה. mistachuzatah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
is saying is like you could read that like a רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir way, you could read like a רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
way, what's to determine which way you're going to read it? It
must be whether your general inclination is to say let's assess things
based on the time of פדיון, pidyon, or let's assess things based
on the time of being מקדיש. makdish. Okay, so רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon who says I'm going to say that when read the פסוק
pasuk to say that now that you're פודה, podeh, we're going to
treat it as a שדה אחוזה s'deh achuzah because now you would
have inherited it, shows his general orientation to define things based on
the time of פדיון. pidyon. And therefore that's how he's choosing to
read that פסוק, pasuk, because if that wasn't his orientation he could
have read the פסוק pasuk like רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. Okay, so
once you see that's your orientation and leads you to read this
פסוק pasuk this way, when you look at this case, that should
also be your orientation and you should define this as one unit
and not as two units.
Alright, so in the same way, is what you're saying the same
as to say what inclined them, the ברייתא, braisa, the logic of
ראויה ra'uyah or not ראויה? ra'uyah?
Yeah, but rather than saying oh they're debating how to read the
letter מם Mem and it's some technical question and he דרשן darshens
a מם Mem this way and he דרשן darshens it, says no,
you could have דרשן darshened the פסוק pasuk however you wanted to
דרשן darshen the פסוק, pasuk, it must be that you have a
particular orientation to this question.
And that led them to the language, to that distinction
and that led them to this debate, but it's because רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon's orientation is to say if you could look at the
time of הקדש hekdesh or at the time of פדיון, pidyon, I'm
going to look at the time of פדיון. pidyon. So that's true,
when it comes to this, you should look at the time of
פדיון pidyon and treat this as one unit
and not as two units. I hope that's the point you're going
to make that you don't even need the פסוק pasuk for some.
Well, that's true too. Okay, anyway let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so it can't, if it's the פסוק, pasuk, where
were we?
אי מהא קרא אימא חדא דעבד אלא לאו משום דאזיל בתר פדיון.
im me-ha kra, eima chada de-avad, ela lav mishum de-azil batar pidyon.
It must be because fundamentally רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon looks at פדיון
pidyon as the key time and therefore he says that in this
case even if you were מקדיש makdish and then the father died,
since at the time of פדיון pidyon it could have been, it
would have been a שדה אחוזה s'deh achuzah had you done you
know, then we treat it as a שדה אחוזה. s'deh achuzah. So
if your orientation is to go by פדיון, pidyon, you should go
by this פדיון pidyon and you should say treat it as one
unit and not as two units. So that's our question. Now that
we've said that this is רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon based on the
fact that it's the tree and not the land underneath etcetera and
we know that there's a רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that goes by
פדיון, pidyon, we want to know here why it goes as two
separate units and not as one. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק
לעולם בעלמא רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון לא אזלי בתר פדיון. Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, l'olam b'alma Rebbi Yehuda v'Rebbi Shimon lo azli basar
pidyon. Nope, we're going to ruin that nice point and say that
it's not a technical issue and we're basically going to make it
a technical issue. Okay, normally רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon would not go by פדיון, pidyon, would go by the
being מקדיש makdish and therefore this way that you were מקדיש makdish
in two stages, you redeem it as two separate units. So why
here do we go by פדיון? pidyon? So והכא קרא אשכח ודריש.
v'hacha kra ashkhach v'daresh. No,
here the פסוק pasuk forced him into it. אין הכי נמי, ein
hachi nami, their general orientation is you look at the stages of
הקדש, hekdesh, if that was two stages then you redeem it as
two stages, they're two separate units. But here, the reason is because
the פסוק pasuk forced them into saying this way. Why did the
פסוק? pasuk? אם כן לכתוב קרא ואם מקנתו אשר לא
אחוזתו. im kein liktov kra v'im mikanato asher lo achuzato. Just say
if it's a purchase field that's not an inherited field. אי נמי
שדה אחוזתו i nami s'deh achuzato that or whatever, an inherited field,
but without the מם. Mem. I was saying the מם Mem before
cause I knew what was coming. מאי אשר לא משדה אחוזתו? mai
asher lo misdeh achuzato?
They were bothered with that extra מם. Mem. They would have been
happy to say like רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, but what's bothering them
was משדה אחוזתו misdeh achuzato which means that it's not even that
there are some types of שדה אחוזה שאינה ראויה להיות שדה אחוזה
יצא זו שראויה להיות שדה אחוזה. s'deh achuzah she-einah ra'uyah l'hiyot s'deh
achuzah, yatzah zo she-ra'uyah l'hiyot s'deh achuzah. So this is a שדה
מקנה s'deh miknah that is not even from, even like it's not
even somehow partly connected, somehow that מם Mem is not saying it's
not that it just isn't a שדה אחוזה, s'deh achuzah, cause in
this case it isn't a שדה אחוזה. s'deh achuzah. It was a
שדה מקנה s'deh miknah that you were מקדיש. makdish. But the משדה
אחוזה misdeh achuzah says it doesn't even come from that world of
things that are a שדה אחוזה. s'deh achuzah. So this field did
come from the world of things that were שדה אחוזות s'deh achuzahs
because it came from a field that the father owned and that
would have, could have been a שדה אחוזה. s'deh achuzah. So really
we want to go by the time of הקדש hekdesh and in
this case you were מקדיש makdish in two stages and therefore it's
two separate units you redeem as two separate units. But here because
it says משדה אחוזה misdeh achuzah it's not so much that we
go by the time of פדיון, pidyon, it's that even when you
were מקדיש makdish this field, what type of a field was it?
It was a שדה מקנה s'deh miknah that was from the universe
of things that were potentially in the future שדה אחוזות s'deh achuzahs
and therefore it's going to have a different status. Yes.
But everything in the land of Israel is going to be somebody's.
No, but not your שדה אחוזה. s'deh achuzah. Now by the way,
it's not just because at the time you were מקדיש makdish it
could have been your שדה אחוזה s'deh achuzah because if that... If
the father had never died, it would still be treated as a
שדה מקנה. sedeh mikneh. So it still does relate to the future
event. Because in the end the father died, now somewhat in hindsight
we're saying that it was from that universe. But nevertheless, they're saying
it's not because of a general orientation that we always go by
פדיון. pidyon. It's that משדה אחוזה mi-sedeh achuzah that says that it
has to be a pure שדה מקנה sedeh mikneh and this was
a שדה מקנה sedeh mikneh that was from the world of שדה
אחוזה.
sedeh
achuzah.
Let me see what we, about the... okay, sounds out there and
we're still maintaining this? Yes.
This is... I don't want to do that right now. It's going
to be confusing. Okay, so.
If the father hadn't died, would you say it's a pure?
That's what I'm saying. It's so... yes, so it's not just that
it could have been a שדה אחוזה. sedeh achuzah. It's that based
on future events we see that it was going to come to
that person as a... as a sort of like a יש ברירה.
yesh bereirah. But a יש ברירה yesh bereirah still given and going
by פדיון. pidyon. We're not looking at things at this time, we're
looking at them at this time, but looking at them at this
time with the benefit of hindsight makes us see that when you
were doing this it was a field that was going to be
your שדה אחוזה. sedeh achuzah.
Yes. But in the end of the סוגיא, sugya, the תנא tanna
here still prefers to build the case on defined reading of a
preposition in a פסוק pasuk than to be satisfied with a general
orientation.
Yes, because it had to fix those two together. But in principle
I'd have no problem with that, right?
I don't think categorically...
But here, right, here, right.
I don't want to make a general statement. Correct, correct. But it's
more comfortable.
Correct, because it solves the problem. Okay.
It's a פסוק. pasuk.
Right. Okay, whew. Now, all right, take a deep breath. We are
now done with that whole הקדש hekdesh רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, the
trees, the land. Okay, I mean not totally done, but let's at
least now wrap things up. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, well
right, the next part is coming up around the corner. אמר רב
הונא חרוב ומורכב דשקמה תורת אילן ליה ותורת קרקע ליה. Amar Rav
Huna charov u-murkav de-shikma torat ilan leh ve-torat karka leh. This thing
is both a tree, this carob and sycamore, and it also is
land, it's like a separate plot of land. We already know it's
a separate plot of land because when you sell the שדה sadeh
with everything in it, you don't sell these trees. These trees are
seen as not a tree in this land but as a separate
plot of land. Okay, but it's also a tree. What does that
mean? Let's take a look. תורת אילן ליה. Torat ilan leh. דהיכא
דאקדיש או זבין שני אילנות והאי יש לו קרקע. De-heicha de-akdish o
zavin shenei ilanos ve-hai yesh lo karka. So how do we know
it's תורת אילן ליה? torat ilan leh? Did I skip a line?
תורת אילן ליה, Torat ilan leh, I did. דהיכא דאקדיש או זבין
שני אילנות והאי יש לו קרקע. De-heicha de-akdish o zavin shenei ilanos
ve-hai yesh lo karka. The principle is when you sell three trees
or you're מקדיש makdish three trees, you sell all the land together
with them. So this, if you sold two pine trees and a
sycamore, you know, or two fig trees and a... and a carob,
so it would be you sold three trees and therefore you get
the land between them. So in that way it's treated like a
tree. תורת קרקע ליה, Torat karka leh, but it's treated not... but
it's also treated as land דלא מזדבן אגב ארעא. de-lo mizdaben agav
ara. That's our משנה. mishnah. When you say this land and everything
in it, you still don't get the carob trees. They're not seen
as a carob tree in this land, it's seen as a separate
plot of land.
So the תנא tanna had to prove that a tree is a
tree and a tree is not a tree. Exactly. I'm just going
to ask, what is the halakhic definition of a tree?
All right, so it depends on the הלכה. halakhah. ואמר רב הונא,
Ve-amar Rav Huna, ואמר רב הונא, ve-amar Rav Huna, עומר שיש בו
סאתים. omer she-yesh bo sa-atayim. Now that we're doing this we're going
to end with some things that are like this that have like
dual status. עומר שיש בו סאתים. Omer she-yesh bo sa-atayim. You've got
a... a bundle of wheat, a sheaf, a sheaf that's... that's all
a sheaf, right? Sheaf, a sheaf of wheat, sheaf of wheat. Say
that ten times fast. Okay, and it has two סאה se'ah in
it, which is a large measure. So is it so big that
it's no longer considered to be a sheaf, then it's just considered
to be I don't know a pile, a pile that you put
a string around? Or is it still a sheaf? So let's take
a look. תורת עומר ליה ותורת גדיש ליה. Torat omer leh ve-torat
gadish leh. It both is considered a sheaf and it's considered a
pile. For what הלכה? halakhah? תורת עומר ליה Torat omer leh דשני
עומרים שכחה. de-shenei omerim shikhchah. There's a הלכה, halakhah, you forgot two
sheaves of collecting them from the... from the field. That's שכחה, shikhchah,
that's ושכחת עומר בשדה. ve-shakhachta omer ba-sadeh. But if you forgot three
sheaves or sheaves, I guess. Sheaves, thank you. If you forgot three
sheaves, all right, three sheaves, then that would not be שכחה, shikhchah,
that would be too much. That would be like, you know, you're
leaving a... you're leaving multiple, you didn't just forget. So if you
forgot two plus this big one, then it's like you forgot three
and none of them are שכחה. shikhchah. Okay, so. תורת
עומר ליה ותורת גדיש ליה. Torat omer leh ve-torat gadish leh. תורת
עומר ליה Torat omer leh דשני עומרים שכחה de-shenei omerim shikhchah
שנים והוא אינם שכחה. shenayim ve-hu einam shikhchah. Two plus this, it's
not שכחה. shikhchah. You don't say, oh no, you forgot two sheaves
plus you forgot a big pile. So the two sheaves are still
שכחה, shikhchah, they don't combine with the big pile. No, you treat
it as three sheaves and you actually... none of them are שכחה.
shikhchah. Okay, that's in... and that's the way this big sheaf is
still considered a sheaf. But תורת גדיש ליה, torat gadish leh, it's
also considered a pile דתנן, de-tenan, עומר שיש בו סאתים. omer she-yesh
bo sa-atayim. סאתים, satayim, שכחה אינו שכחה. shikhcha eino shikhcha. Let's say
you just forgot this one big sheaf that was סאתים, satayim, that
was this size. So this one thing by itself is not שכחה,
shikhcha, it's because you don't say you forgot a sheaf, you—it's a
pile. Okay, so if it's by itself it's not שכחה shikhcha because
it's a pile, but if it's by itself plus two others, it
also makes the two others not שכחה shikhcha because then you say
it's three sheaves. You see that? So it sort of saves you
from שכחה shikhcha in both directions. Okay?
So it has nothing to do with it?
Meaning once—no, the reason of the other two is to say that
it—this one would never be שכחה, shikhcha, but with the other two
if you only considered it a pile, this wouldn't be שכחה shikhcha
and those two would. Because you're also considering it a sheaf, those
two are also not שכחה. shikhcha.
So what would be שכחה? shikhcha? Three sheaves?
No, one or two sheaves.
One or two sheaves? Right, but not more than two. And not
this סאתים. satayim.
If you've got a big pile, okay, you got a big pile,
that's not שכחה. shikhcha. You got a big pile and two sheaves,
this isn't שכחה, shikhcha, these are שכחה shikhcha because it's only two.
But if you've got rather than a big pile, you've got a
huge sheaf, okay, right? So then this isn't by itself because it's
so big we treat it like a pile, but also if it's
this and this, then these also are not because then it's three,
and then these are not שכחה shikhcha either. Okay? So this is
never שכחה. shikhcha. But if it were a pile, it wouldn't help
those other two. But because it's a sheaf, then with those other
two, these other two are also not שכחה shikhcha because then it's
like you forgot three sheaves.
So if you have a situation like that, it's not שכחה, shikhcha,
so what is it?
I just didn't get around to it. Okay,
okay, now,
now, דתנן. detnan. Exactly,
exactly. I haven't forgotten it, I know! Anyway,
fine, דתנן. detnan. עומר שיש בו סאתים, omer she-yesh bo satayim, שכחה
אינו שכחה. shikhcha eino shikhcha. So by itself it's not שכחה, shikhcha,
but it still is a sheaf that it makes the other things
not שכחה shikhcha as well. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר ריש
לקיש: amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Reish Lakish: חרוב המורכב וסדן
השקמה באו למחלוקת רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי ורבנן. charuv hamurkav vesadan hashikma
bau lemachloket Rabbi Menachem berabbi Yossi verabanan. Okay?
So this debate about this חרוב השקמה charuv hashikma etc.,
okay, which is about like you know again which is do you
מקדיש makdish it when you're מקדיש makdish the field, which we have
been saying until now is a debate in our משנה mishna of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן, rabanan, he is saying is,
it's not just רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבנן, rabanan, there's also
the position of רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי. Rabbi Menachem berabbi Yossi. Now
where he gets this, the רשב"ם Rashbam says he must just have
a מסורה mesorah this way. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says ולימא
מחלוקת רבי שמעון ורבנן. velayma machloket Rabbi Shimon verabanan. So why are
you telling me that there's a רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי, Rabbi Menachem
berabbi Yossi, just say that's the מחלוקת machloket in our משנה mishna
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן. rabanan. קא משמע לן
דרבי מנחם ברבי יוסי כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה. ka mashma lan de-Rabbi
Menachem berabbi Yossi ke-Rabbi Shimon sevira leih. He's just trying to tell
you that he has a tradition that says רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי
Rabbi Menachem berabbi Yossi holds like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. A very
like strange way of ending the פרק. perek. But okay, that was
definitely a nice challenge to end the פרק perek with. הדרן עלך
המוכר את הבית. Hadran alach Hamocher et Habayit. Start a new פרק
perek tomorrow.
Give me just one
moment.